Preliminary Guide to the American Economic Association Records, 1886-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American Economic Association records 1886-2008 and undated
American Economic Association.
420.5 Linear Feet 346,763 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Researchers desiring access should consult with the Reference Archivist on duty.
In addition, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The American Economic Association Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2001-2009.
Biographical Note
Primary professional association for economists in the United States, organized in 1885. It publishes the American Economic Review, the Journal of Economic Literature, and the Journal of Economic Perspectives.
Collection Overview
Primarily records of the American Economic Review, (Accession 2001-0118) specifically journal office files consisting of correspondence, manuscript, book review, and referee files (1969-1998). There are also records for the organization (1886-1984) and for its Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP 1972-1993), including histories, reports, minutes, statistics, as well as membership, account, conference, board member, miscellaneous, and newsletter or editorial office files. Some CSWEP material is also present as 371 machine-readable records. There is a small set of journal office records for the Journal of Economic Literature (1975, 1984-1994 and undated). In addition, there are 50 black-and-white photographs of former association presidents, a 39"x10" black-and-white group photograph taken at an unidentified meeting, 48 rolls of microfilm from the various journals (mostly AER), 63 microfiche of Journal of Economic Literature correspondence ([1968]-1980), and 7 reel-to-reel audiotapes.
Addition (2001-0082) (4000 items, 9.6 linear feet; dated 1998-1999) includes records for the American Economic Review, including correspondence and referee files for rejected and withdrawn articles (1998), accepted articles (1999), and papers and proceedings (1999).
Addition (2002-0215) (21000 items, 33.4 linear feet; dated 1999-2001) contains records for the American Economic Review, including editorial correspondence, referee reports, and manuscripts for rejected articles (1999-2000) and accepted articles (March-December 2001) and papers and proceedings (2000-2001). Also includes 37 electronic documents on one floppy disk.
The collection consists of 15 additional accessions dating from 2003 to 2008 with over 200 additional boxes. These additions have not been processed, but are available for research with permission from the American Economic Association. Please consult the Preliminary Description of Unprocessed Collection (below) for details.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
American Economic Association
American Economic Association. Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession
American economic review.
Journal of economic literature.
Economics -- Periodicals
Economics -- Book reviews -- Periodicals
Economics -- Congresses
Economics -- Societies, etc
Economics -- Research
Women economists
Machine-readable records
Black-and-white photographs
Microfilms
Audiotapes
Microfiche
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2001-0118)
  Records of the American Economic Review (225,000 items, dated 1886-1998), specifically journal office files with correspondence, manuscript, book review, and referee files (1969-1998). Also records for the organization (1886-1984) and for its Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP 1972-1993), including histories, reports, minutes, statistics, as well as membership, account, conference, board member, misc., and newsletter or editorial office files. Some CSWEP material is also present as 371 machine-readable records. There is a small set of journal office records for the Journal of Economic Literature (JEL 1975, 1984-1994 and n.d.) In addition, there are 50 black-and-white photographs of former association presidents, a 39"x10" black-and-white group photograph taken at an unidentified meeting, 48 rolls of microfilm from the various journals, 63 microfiche of JEL correspondence ([1968]-1980), and 7 reel-to-reel audiotapes.
  Written permission from AEA required for access to materials less than fifty years old.
  - Minutes of Council and Executive Council, AEA, 1888-1908, and Annual Meetings, 1886-1924
    - AEA. Histories, A.W. Coats, 1952-1963; Journal of Economic Literature, Mark Perlman, editor. Correspondence, [1968] 1970-1980; Organization, [1885]; Minutes, 1886-1904; Membership, 1890-1896 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1902-1906; Membership, 1890-1896; Accounts, 1889-1894; Annual Meetings, 1886-1905 (Box 2)
    - Annual Meetings, 1908-1924 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of Secretary-Treasurer, AEA, including Reports, 1888-1964
    - Correspondence. Incoming, 1888 March- 1896 Febuary (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1893 October-1894 December (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1894-1898 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1898-1899 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, Incoming, 1896-1900 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1900-1902 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1903-1908 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1909; Thomas N. Carver, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1910-1911; Thomas N. Carver, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, including Reports, 1912-1913; Thomas N. Carver, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1914-1915; Allyn A. Young, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1916-1917; Allyn A. Young, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1919; Allyn A. Young, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1922-1923; Ray B. Westerfield, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1924; Ray B. Westerfield, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 19)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1925; Ray B. Westerfield, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1926; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1927; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1928; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1929-1931; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 24)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1932-1933 (A-Z); Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 25)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1933-1935; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 26-27)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1936; Frederick S. Deibler and James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurers (Box 28)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1937-1938; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 29)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1939-1940; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 30)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1940-1941; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 31)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1942; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 32)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1943; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 33)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1944-1945; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 34)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1945-1946; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1947-1948; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 36)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1949-1950; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 37)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1951; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 38)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1952; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 39)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1953; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 40)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1954; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 41)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1955-1956; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 42)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1956-1957; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 43)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1957; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 44)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1957-1958; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 45)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1958; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 46)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1959; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 47-48)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1960; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 49-50)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1961; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 51-52)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1962; Harold F. Williamson, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 53-54)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1963; Harold F. Williamson, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 55-56)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1964; Harold F. Williamson, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 57)
  - Correspondence of Secretary-Treasurer with AEA Committees, Miscellaneous Business, 1930-1961
    - Correspondence: Committees, AEA, and Miscellaneous Business, 1930-1939; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer 1930-1935 and James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer 1936-1939 (Box 58)
    - Correspondence: Committees, AEA, and Miscellaneous Business, 1940-1945 (1959); James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 59)
    - Correspondence: Committees, AEA, and Miscellaneous Business, 1946-1950 (1956); James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 60-61)
  - American Economic Review: Correspondence of Managing Editor, Davis R. Dewey, with editors, contributors, etc.., 1910-1940
    - Correspondence of AEA re founding journal and special editorial correspondence, AER, 1910-1940 (Box 62)
    - AER statistics, 1911-1923; Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1911-1917 (Box 63)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1910-1917 (Box 64-69)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1918-1919 (Box 70-71)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1920 (Box 72)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1921 (Box 73)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1922 (Box 74)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1923 (Box 75)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1924-1925 (Box 76)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1925-1926 (Box 77)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1927-1928 (Box 78)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1928 (Box 79)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1929 (Box 80)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1930 (Box 81)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1931 (Box 82)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1932 (Box 83)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1933 (Box 84)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1934 (Box 85)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1935 (Box 86)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1936 (Box 87)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1937 (Box 88)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1938 (Box 89)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1939 (Box 90)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1940 (Box 91)
  - American Economic Review: Correspondence of Managing Editor, Paul T. Homan, 1941-1951, with editors, contributors, etc.
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1941 (Box 92)
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1942-1943 (Box 93)
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan, Managing Editor, 1941-1951, and Fritz Machlup, Acting Managing Editor, 1944 July-1945 August, with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1944-1945 (Box 94)
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan, Managing Editor, 1941-1951, and Fritz Machlup, Acting Managing Editor, 1944 July-1945 August, with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1945-1949 (Box 95)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, book reviews, articles, and other internal documents
    - AEA internal papers, ca. 1958-1968 (Box 96-104)
    - Foreign correspondence, 1952-1959, 1968 (Box 105-106)
    - Exchanges-Internal memoranda, 1953-1956 (Box 107)
    - Internal memoranda, 1954-1964 (Box 108)
    - Survey articles, 1957-1963 (Box 109)
    - Survey articles; budget; book reviews, 1952-1960, 1963 (Box 110)
    - Book reviews, 1963-1966 (Box 111)
    - Book reviews; general correspondence, 1963-1967 (Box 112)
    - General correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 113-118)
    - General correspondence; articles and correspondence, 1968 (Box 119)
    - Articles and correspondence, 1968 (Box 120-121)
    - Miscellany, 1962-1973, 1980-1982 (Box 122-128)
    - Accounts received for back issues, 1961, (2 bound volumes) (Box 129)
    - General correspondence, 1968-1979 (Box 130-131)
    - Office correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 132-134)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980-1982 (Box 135)
  - C. P. Kindleberger Papers
    - AEA Papers, C. P. Kindleberger, 1984 (Box 136-144)
    - C. P. Kindleberger; AER rejects, prior to 1969 July (Box 145)
  - AER acceptances, rejects, withdrawn, and papers and proceedings
    - AER rejects, prior to 1969 July; 1969-1980 (Box 146-376)
    - AER rejects, comments, and correspondence, 1968-1983 (Box 377-396)
    - AER acceptances and refereed remarks, 1969-1979 (Box 397-432)
    - AER acceptance and rejection cards, 1969-1981 (Box 433-444)
    - AER "No author card" and miscellaneous rejects, 1981-1985 (Box 445)
    - AER rejects, 1981 (Box 446-449)
    - AER rejects, 1982-1983 (Box 450-453)
    - AER published, 1983 (Box 454-457)
    - AER published, 1984 (Box 458-462)
    - AER published, 1985 (Box 463-467)
    - AER rejects, 1983-1985 (Box 468-517)
    - AER rejects, 1985 (Box 518-544)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1986 (Box 545)
    - AER published, 1986 (Box 546-550)
    - AER rejects, 1986 (Box 551-590)
    - AER published, 1987 (Box 591-594)
    - AER rejects, 1987 (Box 595-629)
    - AER published, 1988 (Box 630-633)
    - AER rejects, 1988 (Box 634-664)
    - AER rejects, 1988 (Box 665-669)
    - AEA rejects, 1989 (Box 670-694)
    - AER published 1989 (Box 695-698)
    - AER rejects, 1989 (Box 699-714)
    - AER published, 1990 (Box 715-719)
    - AER miscellaneous, 1987-1988 (Box 720)
    - AER rejects, 1990 (Box 721-748)
    - AER rejects and withdrawn; AER acceptances, 1991 (Box 749-750)
    - AER acceptances, 1991 (Box 751-756)
    - AER rejects, 1991 (Box 757-760)
    - AER rejects, comments and correspondence to, 1991 (Box 761-769)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1992 (Box 770-771)
    - AER acceptances, 1992 (Box 772-778)
    - AER rejects, 1992 (Box 779-790)
    - AER acceptances, 1993 (Box 791-801)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1993 (Box 802)
    - AER rejects, 1993 (Box 803-810)
    - AER acceptances, 1994 (Box 811-818)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1994 (Box 819)
    - AER rejects, 1994 (Box 820-826)
    - AER acceptances, 1995 (Box 827-831)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1995 (Box 832)
    - AER rejects, 1995 (Box 833-839)
    - AER acceptances, 1996 (Box 840-849)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1996 (Box 850)
    - AER rejects, 1996 (Box 851-858)
    - AER acceptances, rejections, and withdrawals, 1997 (Box 859-874)
    - AER acceptances, 1998 (Box 875-888)
  - JEL correspondence, acceptance, and other files
    - JEL correspondence, 1979-[1991?] (Box 889-906)
    - JEL [acceptances?], 1990-1994 (Box 907-915)
    - JEL inactive, 1989-1990 (Box 916-918)
    - JEL office, 1988-1994 (Box 919)
  - AEA office files and Executive Committee records
    - AEA miscellaneous office files, 1955-1983 (Box 920-980)
    - AEA Executive Committee, 1969-1982 (Box 981-986)
  - American Economic Association, Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP), 1971-1996
    - Historical data files, 1971-1974 (Box 987)
    - Historical data subject files, 1972-1974 (Box 988)
      Includes correspondence from other economic associations; committee business and future; Ford Foundation funding proposal (1973); correspondence regarding discrimination cases (Edna Maynard Gott); and hiring practices committee.
    - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 989)
      Includes questionnaires.
    - Roster and correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 990)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 991)
    - 1975 conference at Wellesley College and 1974 survey (Box 992)
      Includes Wellesley Center for the Study of Women in Higher Education and the Professions.
    - Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 993)
    - Budget and CSWEP committee reports, 1972-1977 (Box 994)
    - CSWEP reports, 1973-1976 (Box 995)
      Includes reports by Sonia Pressman, Sonia P. Fuentes, George J. Stigler, Elizabeth Clayton, David M. Gordon, the Boulding-Treagar Report in the AER, and various CSWEP reports.
    - CSWEP meetings at Wellesley College and in New York, San Francisco, Washington, DC, and Atlantic City, 1973-1977 (Box 996)
    - Meetings and reports, minutes and correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 997)
    - Meetings and reports, proposals for CSWEP sessions at AEA meetings, 1974-1987 (Box 998)
    - Correspondence and annual reports, 1980-1987 (Box 999)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1000)
    - Annual report and meetings, 1988-1989 (Box 1001)
    - Meetings, 1989-1992 (Box 1002)
      Includes CSWEP sessions.
    - Board members, meetings, and meeting minutes, 1985-1989 (Box 1003)
    - Board meetings and meeting minutes, 1989-1991 (Box 1004)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 1005)
    - Budget, 1984-1991 (Box 1006)
    - Miscellaneous subject files, A-R, 1974-1988 (Box 1007)
      Includes information on careers for women and careers for women in economics; financial aid; newsletter editorial policy; Federation of Organizations for Professional Women (FOPW); National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER); National Science Foundation (NSF); New York Women Economists; questionnaire results (1974-1989); and research project on women Ph.D. economists, data, proposal, correspondence (1986-1988).
    - Miscellaneous subject files, R-W; membership data, 1981-1989 (Box 1008)
      Includes rosters (1983, 1985, 1987); Roster of Women in Agricultural Economics (1984); correspondence regarding salaries; textbook project; and membership data (1981-1985, including floppy disks 014-015).
    - Membership data, 1985-1987 (Box 1009)
    - Abstracts for papers, 1987-1992 (Box 1010)
    - Newsletters, 1972-1984 (Box 1011)
      Includes newsletter issues and job opportunities.
    - Newsletters, 1985-1987 (Box 1012)
      Includes newsletter issues, correspondence, and articles and clippings for inclusion in newsletter.
    - Newsletters, 1988-1991 (Box 1013)
    - Newsletters, 1991-1992 Winter (Box 1014)
      Includes floppy disk 010, Winter 1992.
    - Newsletters, 1992 Spring-1993 Spring/Summer (Box 1015)
      Includes floppy disks 001 (newsletter labels, 1992), 012 (Spring 1992), 009 (Fall 1992), 005-006 (Spring 1993).
    - Newsletters, miscellaneous, 1977-1991 and undated (Box 1016-1017)
      Includes floppy disk 013 (undated).
    - CSWEP meetings and meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, and other office files, 1989-1991 (Box 1018)
      Includes CSWEP sessions at AEA meetings.
    - CSWEP Meetings and meeting minutes, reports and annual reports, correspondence, and other office files, 1991-1992 (Box 1019-1020)
      Includes CSWEP sessions at AEA meetings and floppy disks 011 (1992), 008 (1991 June 19-1992 Jan. 16), 007 (1992 Jan. 16-1992 May 14), and 004 (1992 May 15-1992 Dec. 21).
    - CSWEP Meetings and meeting minutes, reports and annual reports, correspondence, and other office files, 1993 (Box 1021)
      Includes CSWEP sessions at AEA meetings and floppy disks 003 (1992 Dec. 21-1993 Mar. 26) and 002 (1993 March 26).
    - Published books and reports on women and education and occupations, 1973-1987 (Box 1022)
    - R. Blank CSWEP materials, 1994-1996 (Box 1023-1024)
  - AEA Financial Records, 1962-1988
    - Accounts Receivable
      - Cash receipts, 1970-1981 (Box 1025-1030)
      - Miscellaneous, 1962-1970 (Box 1031-1033)
    - Guide sales, 1965-1969 (Box 1034-1035)
    - Cash disbursements, 1957-1987 (Box 1036-1039)
    - Payroll records, 1951-1988 (Box 1040-1049)
    - General ledger books, 1963-1987 (Box 1050-1053)
    - Audit, investment, and project ledgers, 1958-1969 (Box 1054)
  - Member cards, microfilm, and photographs
    - Member cards, 1900-1975 (Box 1055-1125)
    - Microfilm, (48 rolls) (Box 1126-1128)
      Includes AER vols. 40-65 and vols. 68-70; JEL vols. 8-13 and 16-18; JE Abstracts vols. 2-6; ACLS Parts 1 and 2 (2 rolls each); and JE Perspectives, vol. 2.
    - Photographs (Box 1129)
  - Oversize materials
    - Black-and-white photograph of a group taken at an unidentified meeting, undated, (39"x10") (Opaperfolder 1)
- Accession (2001-0082)
  Addition (2001-0082) (4000 items, 9.6 linear feet; dated 1998-1999) includes records for the American Economic Review, including correspondence and referee files for rejected and withdrawn articles (1998), accepted articles (1999), and papers and proceedings (1999).
  - AER Rejects, A-B, 1998 (Box 1)
  - AER Rejects, B-D, 1998 (Box 2)
  - AER Rejects, D-H, 1998 (Box 3)
  - AER Rejects, H-L, 1998 (Box 4)
  - AER Rejects, L-N, 1998 (Box 5)
  - AER Rejects, N-R, 1998 (Box 6)
  - AER Rejects, R-S, and Withdrawn, 1998 (Box 7)
  - AER Rejects, T-W, and Withdrawn, 1998 (Box 8)
  - AER Rejects, T-V, 1998 (Box 9)
  - AER Acceptances, 1999 March (Box 9-10)
  - AER Papers and Proceedings, 1999 May (Box 10-11)
  - AER Acceptances, 1999 June (Box 12-13)
  - AER Acceptances, 1999 September (Box 13-15)